Superstition

by POUL ANDERSON

Spaceflight by witchcraft — could any concept be more suitable to this magazine which combines (and usually refuses to classify) fantasy and science fiction? This particular blend of themes goes back over three hundred years to the somnium of Johannes Kepler, who was a shrewd enough scientist to realize that witchcraft was a less improbable method of interplanetary flight than any device known to the science of his day. But here, perhaps, is one occasion on which I should classify, and say that, though Kepler s story was a fantasy framing scientific truths, Paul Anderson's fascinatingly blended and balanced tale of a witch in a spaceship is science fiction — if possibly disconcerting to some idolaters of science.

However bold, any achievement remains essentially an adaptation to reality; and the more excellent it is, the more it excludes other possibilities. But reality is ever-changing, not to be encompassed in a merely finite system, so that at last each adaptation must fail. Thus we five with the tragic paradox that all organizations, be they biological species or human societies, are ultimately destroyed by their own virtues.

— Oskar Haeml, Betrachtungen uber die menschliche Verlegenheit

AS HE came through the high darkness, Martin heard them chanting out among the ruins. Overhead the stars were a cold steely sprawl against night, far and far above him; to right and left, the mesa tumbled raggedly away from the road, with a low crescent moon glimmering off sage and stunted trees, a distant icy rise of mountains. He saw torches flare among the hollow shells that had been houses, and his heart paced the muttering of drums.

Equinox was near, and the Utes had come as always to make medicine on the heights. Martin gestured a respectful sign toward the ceremony. It was taboo for him; Base fed the Indians during the dances and shared the favor of their gods, but had its own rites.

The hoofs of his mule clopped loud in chill springtime silence. Grass was thrusting up, tilting the great concrete blocks, gnawing away the road; someday there would only be a rutted dirt track. But Base endured.

Its barbed-wire barricade loomed before him as he rounded the bulky official Stonehenge. The sudden glare of electric lights in his eyes was dazzling. Four musketeers in the leather tunics, blue trousers, and steel helmets of Guardsmen of the Order stood at the gate. Above them spread the sign:

UNITED STATES

ASTRONAUTICAL SERVICE

COLORADO BASE

It had been newly refurbished and hung with protective cow skulls.

“Halt!” The men slanted their flintlocks down. One of them, a youngster made nervous by the Ute devil-masks, fingered a rabbit’s foot; he relaxed when he saw it was only a human on a mule approaching.

Martin reined in and let them see his spaceman’s gray coverall. He was tall and gaunt, with a sunburned hatchet face and lank brown hair. The astronautical warpaint made elaborate loops and jags on his forehead. “Captain Josiah Martin reporting for Mars flight,” he said.

“Oh ... oh, yes, sir.” The corporal of the guard recognized him and fumbled a salute. “How's things in town?”

Martin’s mind ran back to Durango, dusty on the plain below — to wagon trains from as far as Mexico and Canada, California and Wisconsin, to the one wheezy railroad barely kept going by its wizards, to the airport with its occasional priestly jet, warehouses and taverns and smithies, all the roar and bustle of a terminal on the interplanetary line. He thought of his house, Ginny and the kids and the empty nights before them till he came back. If he did; someday somebody would make a slip, the spell wouldn’t be strong enough, and he would ride a flamer down to Earth or drift forever between the stars.

But he was an initiate of the Order, and that was enough.

“So-so,” he answered aloud. “Anything new here at Base?”

“Couple o’ those Injun kids tried to sneak in. Too young to know what taboo means. We gave ’em back to their folks for ritual cleansing and a good spanking.”

“Indians don’t spank their children,” said Martin absently. “But the cleansing ought to throw a healthy scare into them. I don’t suppose they did any damage?” “Nothing serious. They came within a yard of the power plant, so the Old Man sacrificed a dog just to be on the safe side.” The corporal opened the gate. “Good luck, sir. Say hello to the girls on Mars for me,”

The spaceman rode through. Ahead of him stretched the field, an enormous waste of ferro-concrete rimmed with crumbling buildings. The old ones were mostly abandoned — tradition said they had held clerks, security personnel, vips, and other esoteric types, back in the superstitious days. Ritual was much simpler now, fewer initiates needed, so many of the steel-and-glass giants were empty or had been torn down to make the small huts which were all the modern age required.

Passing the barracks and the messhall, Martin saw a KP setting out a bowl of milk for the Good Folk, and nodded approval.

The blockhouses around the firing pits were unchanged. They had been built for strength alone. He spied the enormous hulk of a Stage One looming in its gantry, the metal sides hurling back floodlit glare, Mechs swarmed over it, making the final checks and spells, renewing the potent Eagle sign etched and painted on the hull.

The nuclear ship proper, Phobos, was dwarfed by the Stage One, out of whose mouth she reached like a little steel fish half swallowed by a shark.

Martin rode around the field, toward the astrologer’s tower. This was one of the few ancient buildings still in use, a leaping immensity whose glass-bricked lower wall was a cold green shimmer in the light. He dismounted outside, turning his mule over to an attendant, and walked into the lobby.

The girl at the newsstand smiled at him. “Hi, Captain,” she said. “What’ll it be tonight?”

“Oh . . . make it the usual. Twenty bucks. I don’t think I’ll need more than standard luck this trip.” He signed the chit and received the token. A good deal of a spaceman’s pay went for sacrifices.

The warlock at the dispatcher’s office took his corban and admitted him. He washed his hands, prostrated himself before the orrery, and danced seven times widdershins about it intoning the laws of Kepler and the elements of Earth’s and Mars’ orbits. The miniature planets spun flickering in stillness, only the faint noise of clockwork was like distant laughter.

Making another prostration, Martin backed out of the office and went upstairs. The astrologer’s lab was on the second floor, and half a dozen young apprentices, earnest in their zodiacal robes, were working out Earth-Wheelstar paths for the coming year on a big computer. Their chief, Major Savage, stood looking out of the window at the spacefield.

“Oh . . . good evening, captain.” He turned around. There was a ghost of worry on the bearded face. “You’re late.”

“The railroad train had broken down across the road,” apologized Martin. “I had to wait till they could get it started again.”

“Mmm . . . yes. Glad you did.”

“Why — what else was there to do?”

“Some of the boys are pretty reckless. They’d go around the train. It’d never occur to them that a Power might have stalled the thing right there for the purpose of holding up traffic.”

Martin shook his head. Spacemen learned to be careful.

Of course, the Power could have done it for malignant reasons, but it could just as well be benevolent. Perhaps the delay had kept him from an accident he would otherwise have had. On the whole, you were better off taking signs at face value.

Savage glanced at the clock. ‘‘Your omens were only lair, but nothing to be alarmed about. You'll blast off at midnight if the weather holds. I’ll have to check with the homunculus on that; there’s a cold front moving down from Wyoming, and you know what a sudden strong wind can do to foul a takeoff. But I think it’s all okay.” He lit a cigaret with nervous yellow-stained fingers.

“Usual crew, I reckon?”

“Well — Not exactly. You’ve got Dykman and Peralta on engines as before, but a new witch and —”

“What happened to Juliet?” Savage grinned, half exasperated.

“What d’you think? In two weeks she’ll be Mrs. Geoffrey Roberts.”

“Maybe love does make the world go ’round,” drawled Martin, “but it sure makes it tough keeping a good witch.”

“Fortunately,” said Savage, “Colorado Springs Coven had just graduated a new girl with honors, so I swore her in fast before some other outfit should get her, Valeria Janosek, age eighteen.”

“Eighteen? That’s pretty old for a witch to start.”

“She began late. I understand her people were immigrants from the Great Lakes Thalassocracy or the Kingdom of Upper Michigan or some such place. Old Believers, so she was all of twelve before the Coven persuaded her to join. But she’s got the Power all right, and should have thirty useful years in her.”

“Nuts! If she’s not a beast, she won’t stay celibate that long. Well, the Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away. Isn’t Rogers going to be supercargo?”

“Sorry, no. His kid was sick, and to cure the boy he had to take a geas. No space flight this year. You’ve got one Philip Hall."

Martin raised his brows. “Any relation to the Boss?”

“Nephew.” Savage tugged his beard unhappily. “He’s going to give trouble, I’m afraid. He’s been studying at Boulder — good physics department, but you know what a hotbed of Old Believers the place, is. Seems to have blotted up some crazy notions of theirs . . .” His voice trailed off.

Grimness lay on Martin’s mouth. “I’ll ride herd'on him. Once we’re under weigh, I’m the final authority.”

“Take it easy, though. He is a Hall, and you don’t get rough with a nephew of the Boss of Colorado.”

“I’ve got a ship and a cargo and five lives to get through. No half- baked kid is going to ignore the regs while I’m captain.”

Savage puffed his cigaret and looked away, into the electric night. He’d tried to discourage the boy; but family pressure —

The Order had the spiritual power, and Base was the seat of the Order. But the Boss had the cannon and cavalry. Someday there was going to be a showdown between the temporal and ghostly authorities.

Savage hoped it wouldn’t come in his lifetime.

He went over the flight plan with Martin. It would be a short and thunderous hop up to the Wheel-star, a brief preparation there, acceleration, and the weeks-long orbiting to Mars. All known meteor swarms were safely off the path, but you could never be sure.

They went into the darkened offside room where the homunculus lay. Pale-blue idiot eyes looked up at them out of a swollen head. Savage performed the needful rites, and a weary voice told them the storm wouldn’t arrive till 0130. Then: “Go away. Wake me not.” The thing slipped back into mindlessness.

Having settled the technical details, Martin crossed over to the ready room for briefing. His crew were there, and he stood for a moment in the door, considering them.

The engineers he knew: stolid blond Dykman, dark little Peralta, good sober spacehands. Supercargo Lieutenant Philip Hall was a slender handsome youth, light curly hair above a pale taut countenance. Witch 1/C Valeria Janosek was more of a surprise,

Martin had expected the usual thin, twitching frame and hungry eyes of a Power vessel. Valeria had a beautiful .build on her, a high- cheeked straight-nosed hazel-eyed face, a subdued manner but a ruddy shout of hair falling to her shoulders. She sat calmly under the admiring glances of her shipmates.

Either the Power was very weak in her — and Savage had sworn it was not — or she had mastered it so well that she could be a whole human as well as a Covener. If the latter were true, she was ideal; the hysterics of the ordinary witch were a major hazard of space travel. But a good-looking non-neurotic was unlikely to remain celibate very long.

Heigh-ho, You can’t win.

Martin went to the desk as they rose. “In the name of Almighty God and the Powers He has seen fit to give charge of this galaxy — well met,” he intoned. “We are gathered for briefing ere we venture past the sky to Mars. Let none remain with us whose hands and heart are not clean, who has eaten forbidden food or done forbidden deeds, and who is not at peace with the Elementals. But that man and that woman who are clean and fit, them shall the Powers ward, here and between the stars and on ail worlds, even unto the end of time. Search your souls, all spaccfarers, be sure you are prepared, that you have your talismans and have made your sacrifices and are guilty of no transgression for which penance has not been done.”

They proceeded carefully through the ritual, slaughtering a black rooster which a technician brought and sprinkling the blood in the witch-bowl. Martin caught the scorn of young Hall; it was ail the boy could do to go through with the passes and responses. Valeria was also giving the youth some worried glances.

At the close of the session, she checked their obeahs and tattoos. “All in order, sir.” She saluted Martin crisply.

“Then come,” he said. “The Wheelstar awaits.”

Briefing over, they relaxed formality, shook hands all around and had a final smoke together. Martin strolled over to Hall, where the latter stood gazing out the window at the field.

“First trip, isn’t it, son?” he asked.

Hall nodded. “Yes, sir.” His voice was strained.

“Nothing to be scared of. It’s all in order, every word said and every demon battened down tight. All you have to do is tend our tobacco on the way out and the Martian gan-drug on the way home.”

Sweat was a film on the unlined forehead. “Are you sure it’s all right? How about the — the physical side of it? How well do those mechs know their business?”

“Damn well, son. It’s been checked down to the last gasket; and every man had the relevant volume of the Books beside him as he worked. Why, they replace the hydrazine valves after every blast just on principle, whether they look bad or not, and that in spite of what those Durango artisans charge.”

Hall tried not to shudder as he regarded the monstrous Stage One. “We have to ride up on that? When a nuclear engine is so simple and foolproof?”

“We’ll go on nuclear from the Wheelstar.”

“Why not from Earth?”

Martin held out two fingers against evil, “That’s taboo,” he said sharply. “Haven’t you learned your Ars Thaumaturgica?

“Curses harshly long and cruel if thou use atomic fuel ere thou’rt safe beyond the air: burnt-out eyes and shedded hair, deadly sickness in the nations, monsters in three generations!"

Hall nodded, stiffly, “I’ve heard it. I am an initiate, captain. But do you know why that rule exists?”

“Certainly. It’s an elementary example of sympathetic principles. The sun and stars belong in the sky. Nuclear reactions go on in the sun and stars. Therefore nuclear reactions belong in the sky. Q.E.D.”

“Ever hear of radioactivity?”

Martin made another V. “Who hasn’t? Best not to talk of such matters, son.”

“No,” said Hall bitterly. “Don’t even think about it. Don’t try to design a firing pit that makes it safe to use an atomic blast, fust go on in the old way, because we're scared to find out anything new.”

“They tried a lot of stuff back in the Dark Ages. Hadn’t learned the proper rituals, I reckon. So naturally the Elementals broke loose, and you got war, famine, plague, breakdown . . . We know better in the modern age.” Martin knocked out his pipe and looked at his watch. “Time to sashay along, folks.”

At the doorway, a wizard 3/C handed him his copy of the Book: Astrogator s Manual and Ephcmerides, with its tooled-leather binding and its illuminated tables of logarithms. He took it respectfully under his arm and led the way to the Phobos.

Stage One blasted, thunder crashed through the midnight mesa and the Utes made good-hick medicine. There was a close magical as well as commercial relation between them and the white man. Their dances assured the annual return of the seasons (or, in Base theory, that Earth stayed safely on her orbit). The ships of the Order brought back useful products that could only grow on Mars or Venus — such as gan-drug, which when properly mixed with snakeskins and graveyard herbs cured the Bleeding Sickness that the carelessness of the ancients had unleashed.

Up the ship rose, flinging herself into the sky on flame. At two hundred miles altitude, the exhausted Stage One shell dropped off. The Phobos rose another fifty miles on momentum, after which Martin used a short nuclear blast to get into orbit for the Wheelstar.

Stage One tumbled back toward Earth. Its parachute bloomed white against indifferent stars, and it fell in leisurely fashion along a path made unpredictable by stratospheric winds. Base could have tracked it with radar or homunculus, but didn’t bother; there weren’t men or resources available to fetch it, so other arrangements had been made. Nearing the ground, it fired off a star shell, and then crunched sagebrush beneath its mass.

The burst was seen by a Navaho sheepherder who swore in exasperation; but he knew the geas, and duly informed his chief next morning. The chief was not very happy about it either, and inspected the rocket himself. Yes — it bore the Eagle sign, with blighting curses for all who failed to return it to Base. The chief got men and wagons, and trekked seventy miles with the unwieldy thing. His own people benefitted by what the Order brought to Earth, but he would never have taken the trouble except for the sure knowledge that disobedience meant ruin, barren herds and sickness in the hogans.

The Phobos came smoothly in to the Wheelstar and clamped fast. The station gang emerged to pump reaction mass into her tanks. They were shorthanded up here, and Martin had to help with the ceremonies: sympathetic magic in which the ship’s Book was moved across a map from Earth to Mars while the equations of a 135^0 orbit were recited. The rest of his crew had time off.

Spacesuited, Hall and Valeria walked around the Wheelstar. Its spoked circumference rotated, ponderous and quiet, they needed the boots which a warlock artisan had magnetized and chanted over. This place was loaded with mana; if you didn’t always keep one foot against it, you were flung into space — “down” was radially away from the cabins at the hub.

Earth hung huge and beautiful before their eyes, aurora streaming about the white North Pole, bands of cloud and storm, the dark mass of continents. Even as they watched, the Wheelstar moved around till the desolated wilderness of the Eastern Hemisphere was visible. They could see the great lifeless areas, ashen leper-spots against the green and brown of uncursed land.

The girl’s face was tinted blue by the Earth-glow, but was not less good to look on. Behind the glassy helmet, she stared in awe. “It was worth it,” she said at last. “It was worth living with the Coven, to come here.”

“Are they that bad?” asked Hall.

Her voice was tinny in the radio: “No. They’re all right — the girls are rather odd, they’re apt to throw fits and so on, but no harm is meant. Some of the rituals scared me, though. And then living in that castle on Pike’s Peak, with all the bats —” Her tone snapped off, half frightened. “I can’t say more.”

Hall spoke slowly, not wanting to antagonize her: “I don’t really see why you joined the Coven, I’m told your people are Old Believers.”

“Yes. I hated to hurt them. But the recruiting sergeant showed me some of the spells . . . and he was right! He explained the modern spirit to me. I —” She was looking at him, as if pleading to be understood. “I couldn’t see living in the past, hanging on to obsolete superstitions. It was so futile. I wanted to be part of the world and its work.”

Hall felt a twisting within himself. “Do you really think this . . . thaumaturgy... is something new?”

“Oh, no, of course not. We had classes in history. They said it was the First Way, the one in which man became man. But then during the Dark Ages people got misled. They thought everything could be done by engines and — There were only a few who kept the truth alive, secret Covens, hex doctors in Pennsylvania, voodoo priests in Haiti . . . that sort. People as a whole had to discover through suffering that their own beliefs were false; then they turned back to the First Way.”

Hall nodded jerkily. His voice came fast: “You have the right facts, Val, but the wrong interpretation. The truth is this. Even in the age of science, there was always a substratum of ignorance and irrationality; the man who flew a jet faster than sound very often carried a good-luck charm, and so on. When the War came, and civilization went smash, the educated people — who concentrated in the cities — suffered most; the backward countrymen survived in larger numbers. Add to that the anti-scientific reaction, and you very naturally got a belief in witchcraft winning general acceptance. Since then, it’s been a matter of elaborating that belief, rationalizing it — but it’s still superstition!”

He heard her suck in a shocked breath. “Phil! You don’t really mean that!”

“I sure as hell do.” The throttled anger of a decade boiled up in him. “I certainly do, and I’m going to say it if it costs me my life.”

“But how — Phil, can’t you see?"

“I can. In fact, I believe in using my own eyes, rather than taking somebody elsc’s word. They have a pretty complete scientific library at Boulder: not just those how-to-do-it manuals that pass for science today, but fundamental knowledge, the history and philosophy of science itself. I went through all I could find. I did some of the experiments, and they worked —”

“Of course they did,” Her eyes widened in puzzlement. “Why shouldn’t they? The ancient magic was pretty potent.”

“Damn it, it isn't magic! It’s . , . it’s the nature of things!”

She shook her head, the long hair swirling in its glazed cage. “Things are what they are. I don’t see what you’re so worked up about. It’s in the nature of things that an oscillatory circuit should generate radio waves, just as it’s in the nature of things that a rain dance brings rain.”

“But suppose you hold the dance and no rain comes?” he challenged.

“Why, then there was some counter-influence, of course,”

“That’s it,” There was a demanding harshness in his tone. “You always cover up, explain away. There isn’t any method to disprove your ideas about magic — so they’re meaningless.”

A friendly mockery curved her lips. “Suppose your radio circuit foils to work?” she asked.

“Then there’s something wrong with it.”

“Exactly! So where’s the difference?”

“Just this: I can find out what’s wrong, and correct it.”

“If a rain dance foils,” she told him, “the chief warlock investigates, finds out what he thinks was amiss, makes amends, and holds another dance. Sooner or later, he locates the cure and the dance does work. As for you, Lieutenant Hall, I don’t think your radio always gets fixed on the first try!”

He looked at her with something close to wildness. “I’ve been through this before,” he said between his teeth. “There’s only one way to fight it. On this voyage, I’m going to prove to you that no magic is needed to make the trip safely.” Shock held her unstirring. The Wheelstar spun slowly through a cold silence. “No,” she said at last. “If you endanger the ship, I’ll have to report you.”

He said, almost pleading: “You’re too . . . fine a girl, to live with owls and bats, or go to those filthy Sabbats. I want to end.it for— you, as well as everyone alive.”

She made no answer, but walked from him. Earth loomed behind her, big and scarred.

Perhaps it was only Hall’s heresy, but Valeria had an uneasy feeling about this voyage. She thumbed through her books and sacrificed a cockroach — the ship could carry no larger animal; even her Siamese familiar must stay at home — but the truth remained hidden.

That was the trouble with second sight, she thought bleakly. It was always unreliable, more art than thaumaturgy. A creepy sense might be authentic forevision or might only be an upset stomach. The wildest and trickiest of the Elemental were those which governed the Timeflow.

And there was a dreadful weight of responsibility for such a young pair of shoulders. It was more than lives and cargo; the ship herself was beyond price. It took the artisans ten years to replace a lost spaceship.

Not for the first time, she cursed the blind greed of the Dark Ages, If they had not drunk petroleum in rivers, gutted the ores and gulped the coal, men would not now have to ride on horse and oxcart in a painful search after the necessities. If they had saved forests and topsoil and water tables, the world would not be a thin crust of civilization, a few sharded sovereignties in the Western Hemisphere, above a gape of starveling savagery. If they had not hurled nuclear thunderbolts, there would be no Cursed Craters where death still laired, no Bleeding Sickness or generations of monsters.

Well — they hadn’t known any better. Not the least of their superstitions had been that man was all-powerful and could always escape the consequences of his own acts. It was the task of the modern age to rebuild.

She donned her uniform, the black dress and peaked hat, took a forked willow twig in hand, and went down the length of the Phobos. From the small control cabin where Captain Martin sat unresting, past the cramped wardroom and its curtained bunks, the gyro housing and air-water plants, to the engine room, she made her way.

At one gravity acceleration, Earth was dropping behind and Mars was a sullen red star near the blinding sun.

The twig remained quiescent till she entered the engine section. There it twisted in her hands. She felt the queer mindless tension of rising Power, surrendered soul to it, and let the dowser have its way. Return to consciousness and the engineers’ worried eyes was like swimming up through a dark rushing river.

“Potential neutron leakage here.” She pointed to the after bulkhead and its shuddering dials. “Not imminent, but you better prevent it now.”

Peralta sighed with relief and tapped a jug of holy water — deuterium oxide. Valeria said the spells over it while Dykman was assembling a patch plate. It fitted neatly, the holy water was poured into it, the neutrons would bounce back when they emerged,

“All clear.” The girl smiled. “Ship’s OK otherwise.” She did not mention her forebodings.

Dykman shuffled his feet. “What do you think of our supercargo?” he asked.

“Why —” Valeria paused. “He seems like — a nice guy.” Irrationally, in the teeth of all evidence, she thought he was the nicest guy she had yet known.

“I wonder, Val. I don’t like to say anything against a shipmate, but , . . well, damn it —”

“What we want to know,” said Peralta bluntly, “is whether his opinions are likely to be dangerous.”

“Oh . . . he’s been talking to you, too? I don’t think so. He’s entitled to his beliefs, right or wrong.”

“Yes, but as I understand the theory, belief is important — sympathetic effect. His opinions may act to nullify our spells.”

An anger she could not explain to herself chilled the witch’s reply: “I’m the judge of that.”

“Oh, sure, sure,” said Peralta. “No offense meant, Val. I. only wanted your professional analysis.”

“You have it.” She went haughtily out of the room.

The ship thrummed around her, lancing through a night of stars and empty distance. She felt a nagging guilt. In all honesty, it was entirely possible that counter-belief had a counter-effect; one of the Coven professors had entertained a hypothesis that this was why magic had worked so ill in the Dark Ages.

But she couldn’t be sure. And the mere suspicion might make the captain order that Hall be pitched out the airlock.

She saw him emerging from the cargo hatch and paused. His face lit up, boyishly. “Where’ve you been?” he asked.

“On duty. And you too, I suppose." Why did her heart flutter?

Hall nodded. “Have to turn that tobacco over every watch, or it’s likely to start molding. I wish we had decent fungicides.’’

“What are they?”

“Hm? Oh . . . chemicals to kill the mold.”

“But mold is a curse,” she protested. “A curse of dark Powers. That’s why sunlight and fresh air prevent it.”

A lopsided grin twitched his mouth. “Have it your way. But in the old days they sprayed their crops —”

“I know. And thus protected weakly stock, rather than breed strains which could resist. And ate and drank the poisons themselves, with no real proof that the amount was harmless to them.”

“There were mistakes made,” he agreed. “But nothing which couldn’t have been corrected in time. And men spread over Earth; and every man — not just a warlock or a priest or a Boss — rode behind engines instead of horses; and Mars and Venus were colonized; and nature was man’s slave.”

Valeria stamped her foot. “So they thought!” she said. “They thought they could chain nature, their mother, even the nature within themselves. They thought they could fight, and mine, and erode, and breed without limit — science was bound to solve the problems that arose, oh, yes. They thought that man was a chosen race and exempt from natural law —”

“Not at all!” Hall’s eyes burned with a missionary eagerness, “It was precisely by understanding the laws of nature that they could control her. It’s this age which has crept back into ignorance.”

“In other words,” she said thinly, “the laws of physics are all the laws of nature there are?”

“Why . . . yes. Ultimately, phenomena reduce to —”

She whirled and stalked down the corridor, the long black dress flowing about her. When she had reached the sanctuary of her bunk, she drew the curtain and lay there and wept.

She didn’t know why. But the Power within a human heart acts strangely.

On orbit, the Phobos cut blast and let the sun’s invisible arm swing her toward Mars.

Weightlessness was an eerie thing, like endless falling, and Hall was miserably sick till he got used to it. For Valeria it was also new, but a witch had enough self-mastery not to be troubled. Nevertheless, Martin observed how she moped about.

He was inclined to shrug it off. Female Coveners were a peculiar lot, and she was better than most he’d lifted with. Typically, a witch was an arrogant hag or a skinny girl at the obnoxious nadir of adolescence; frustration and the nerve-tightening forces they worked with made them poor company.

There were always small jobs aboard, puttering, repair and maintenance, the ship was deliberately built to keep men busy, Between times, they had their amusements, books and games. Hall turned out to be an excellent poker player.

Martin found himself liking the boy. Hall was careful to hold his family connections in the background and ask no special favors; he was going to space because of a genuine desire to travel. If at times he was sulky and withdrawn, that was his privilege.

In fact, the only objection to him was the superstition he had absorbed at Boulder, He'd never make a spaceman till he unlearned that.

It was customary for the skipper to instruct and rehearse a junior officer in the art. Hall was an apt pupil, with quite a flair for mathematics; mechanically speaking, he was excellent. But on the ritual —

Martin decided, a week out, to bring matters to a head.

They were in the pilot room, a narrow chamber stuffed with instruments and controls, a periscope for viewing the outside. Hall had just torn down and reassembled the radar under Martin’s eye — no easy task in null-gee. “You’ll do, son,” said the captain.

Hall looked up unsurely. “Isn’t it dangerous?” he asked. “I mean, not to have the radar going while we’re on orbit.”

“What in the Black Name for? You use your radar to help you approach a Wheelstar, that’s all,”

“But meteors — Look, the spaceships in the old days had a radar sweep hooked to an autopilot. When it spotted a meteor coming, it activated the blast and got out of the way.”

“That was the theory,” said Martin dryly. “In practice, you can’t detect a meteor at sufficient distance to fix its orbit accurately. So the ship would make unnecessary swerves, use up her reaction mass, maybe not have enough for deceleration. These quick-transit paths, like our own right now, save time but waste fuel; maybe you don’t know what a narrow safety margin we have. So it’s a lot more practical to let your witch use her foresight and warn you hours ahead of time.”

Hall exploded. His fist came down on the recoil chair’s arm. Since he had neglected to keep a knee bent around the stanchion, he went cartwheeling into the air. Martin laughed, reached out, and drew him back.

“Take it easy, son,” he advised.

“But — damn and blast it! You mean we’re actually trusting our lives to a hysterical woman’s hunches?”

“Don’t slander your shipmates,” said Martin sharply. Then, seeking tact: “After all, the probabilities are on our side. I admit foresight doesn’t always work, but the chances of getting clipped by a rock are small anyway,”

“I know,” said Hall in a harsh tone. “I know that. But I also know that computer research could give us a radar-pilot system which would really do the job. And nobody’s undertaking the research!”

“Matter of economics,” shrugged Martin. “Let’s say that failure of foresight costs us one ship a century — ten years’ work by highly skilled men. Under present conditions, where precision tools are so scarce, it’d take maybe three years to build such a computer for each ship . . . quite apart from the time and brains which the initial research would tie up, and which are needed elsewhere.

“Thanks to those lunatics back in the Dark Ages, man’s living on a mighty small margin. Someday we’ll rebuild and have a big surplus, but meanwhile we have to struggle along with what we’ve got. And anyway, by that time foresight should be well enough understood to make your computer unnecessary.”

The frankness in the blue eyes before him was of anger. “So you say! You and your witless faith! What was it pulled man out of the caves? Magic? Subconscious maunderings identified with revelation or foresight? Hell, no! It was working with, understanding and controlling, the real world!”

“Of course it was,” said Martin. “I’ve studied history too, for your information. The first men to chart the stars were Babylonian astrologers. The Greeks developed geometry because number and relation were sacred things. The alchemists learned a lot about matter. European witches cured dropsy with toadskins, and South American medicine men discovered quinine.”

“That’s beside the point!” stormed Hall. “This ship couldn’t have been built by ... by magic. It could only have designed by a science which had discarded superstition.”

“Well . . . let’s say a science which made simplifying assumptions, thereby cutting the problem down to a size men of that epoch could handle. But the assumptions were obviously false.”

"False? They were verified by observation!”

“Yeah? How about Newton’s law of inertia? Pure fiction: there is and can be no body in the universe moving only by its own inertia. There are always forces, resisting media — For that matter, what is this energy the physics books talk about? Kinetic energy is motion, potential energy is position; but both position and motion are relative. How can any sane man believe energy is an absolute quantity when he can’t possibly find a zero point?

“Energy, inertia, entropy, force— all the basic concepts of physics— they’re mathematical constructs which give useful results. Identifying those equations with reality is mighty bad semantics.”

Martin stopped, wishing he could tamp his pipe and blow dogmatic clouds; but —

Spaceships, run by demon Fire, swiftly feel the demon’s ire. Light no flame aboard the boat lest smother'd Air's ghost grip thy throat.

“Oh, you’re glib enough,” said Hall bitterly. “You know how to use an ephemerides or an elliptic function. But do you understand them? I doubt it. You don’t see that the philosophy which created them denied your magical folderol.”

“So it did,” said Martin levelly. “And it was wrong, of course.”

“But — damn it, witchcraft doesn’t work!"

“The hell it don’t, son. Every year the Utes make medicine to keep Earth on her orbit; and Earth stays there. Use your common sense."

“But you’re arguing post hoc. In the old days, they didn’t have those dances, and Earth still —”

“Oh, but they did. There were always backward tribes, so-called, hex doctors, witch-wives; there was always a little ritual, at least.”

“How about the ages before there were any men?”

“That’s been argued about. I incline to the will-o£-God theory myself. God made man intelligent and turned over a lot of responsibility to him.”

“But —”

“Look. What’s the test of truth — the only test we have? Isn’t it whether a concept works? Whether it gives tiie results it’s supposed to?”

“Yes, of course. But —”

“So Base is taboo to non-initiates. They could meddle around with ... oh, say a hydrazine tank and blow us all to Sathanas.

“So I dance around the orrery reciting astronomical equations. Result: I know them cold.

“So it’s taboo to use nuclear blasts on Earth. You ought to know those blasts can be deadly.

“So a Stage One bears a hex sign. It compels whoever finds it, to return it to us. We can’t build a new Stage One for every flight —we have to have them back!

“So people in general go through the rites, and observe the Law, and abide by the taboos. It gives them a sense of security; we don’t have the unrest and the incidence of demoniac possession — I reckon you’d call it psychosis — they did in the Dark Ages. It keeps them in line, orders society as society has got to be ordered if it’s to function without needing all the police and restrictive government they had in the past. It keeps people out of trouble: they may not know about radiation, most of ’em being illiterate, but they do know the Cursed Craters arc forbidden. It makes them believe in the hex doctor, and belief is a big help in curing them.

“No, no, son. Magic works. You see it working every day of your life.”

Hall leaned forward, triumphantly, His forefinger stabbed at the captain’s chest. “Ah, hah! I’ve got you now! You’re admitting that any value the rites have is merely pragmatic.”

“No, I’m not,” said Martin. “I’m just pointing out that there is a pragmatic, everyday usefulness . . . which is more than you can say for most of the Dark Age concepts. Besides this, of course, there’s the matter of natural law. For instance, we carry a witch on every ship not just to reassure us, though self-confidence is important, but to —”

Hall shoved from his chair, violently, and went sailing out the exit. Martin stared after him. A worried frown grew between the captain’s brows.

Similarity — Burn a man’s photograph, and the man dies unless he has counter-spells. Believe you have foresight, and often you will have. Believe you are in a ship of madmen doomed by their own lunacies, and you may well generate doom.

Martin knew what would happen to him if he sent the Boss’ nephew out the airlock. But he knew, as well, what might happen if he didn’t.

Grimly, he weighed the probabilities.

Philip Hall went hurtling down the corridor and gulping for air. The thunder of his heart drowned the noise of ventilators, the million miles of loneliness vanished in his rage.

Blindness!

Always it had been there, the immemorial muttering current of Stone Age superstition. Don’t break mirrors. Don’t walk under ladders. Carry a rabbit’s foot. Nail a horseshoe over your door. Turn back if a black cat crosses your path. Maybe the captain was right in one sense: maybe man was by nature a huddler in the dark, maybe reason was only a thin precarious membrane ripped apart by the first gust of fear.

They had come out of the caves, out of roadless mountains and tumbledown huts and tropical jungles, witches and warlocks spilling across the world. Science was smashed and discredited, the half-melted snag of a skyscraper stood against smoking heaven like a grisly question mark, there was no faith left in the wolves’ den which Earth had become. Small wonder that bats should flutter about the heads of witches, Covens meet on high hills, blessings and blastings chant from withered lips; small wonder that the race had turned back to its first beliefs.

But in God’s name, now they had rebuilt; however small and weak, civilization existed again. How could they recreate what their ancestors had owned without the rational minds of those mighty dead? What would they ever be but barbarians till someone had lifted the night from their brains?

He saw Valeria afloat near her bunk, looking blank-eyed into nothing. Weightless, her skirt drifted about trim streaming legs. The fury congealed within him, hardened and cooled to a brittle crystalline mold.

“Val,” he said.

The coppery head turned to his, hazel eyes focused and a small startled smile tilted her lips. “Oh . . . hello, Phil.”

“What were you thinking of?” he asked awkwardly.

“Never mind.” Color stained the pale smooth cheeks.

“I’m afraid —” He stopped, hunting for words. “I’m afraid I just had a run-in with the skipper.”

She bit her lip. “You should be more careful, Phil. I can’t counteract your influence all the time.”

“What influence?” He grinned sourly. “I’m making no converts, if that’s what you’re thinking of.”

“It isn’t. It’s your . . . state of mind. I’ve been having ugly dreams; I hope they aren’t forerunners.”

“And it’s my fault?” He felt a slumping. “I’m sorry. I — don’t want to worry you.”

“Well . . . maybe it’s no doing of yours anyhow. Maybe we’ve run into bad medicine regardless.” The girl shivered. “Sometimes I wish I’d never joined the Coven. It isn’t always easy.”

He wanted to spit. His fists gathered at his side. “It’s not right,” he mumbled. “I’ve seen enough witches . . . poor scared kids, tormented by their own twisted nerves . . . and now you."

“There are always those whose work is hard,” she answered gravely. “Even in those old days you’re so romantic about, there must have been people whose occupations wore them down.” A hand fell shyly on his. “Don’t be sorry for me, Phil, Witchdom has its compensations.”

“Do you mean always to —”

“Oh, probably not. I’ll doubtless be getting married eventually, if the right man comes along.” She didn’t meet his eyes.

“Now there,” he gibed, “is one example of ridiculousness. Why should a biological incidental like virginity determine whether you have the Power or not?”

“It’s not exactly an incidental ... ask any woman. You might as well ask why it should determine whether I have children or not.” They were drifting free, moving slowly on air currents in an. empty wardroom. The hex symbols covering the walls spun in the man’s vision as he turned. Somehow, it was a dream, this floating in stillness was not altogether real, and —

And in a dream —

He pulled her to him, roughly, and kissed her.

He felt how she stiffened. Then her struggle sent them awhirl in the air, caroming off wall and floor with a brutal force. She clawed after his eyes and he let her go, appalled at the savagery. She drifted from him shuddering and crying.

He pushed against a stanchion and arced toward her. “I’m sorry,” he said frantically. “I didn’t know—”

Through shaking hands, she answered: “There’s a d-death penalty for that . . . molesting a, a, a witch on orbit —”

Strength drained from him, he hung soul-naked while the hungry vacuum pressed close to the hull around.

“No,” he said. “Not for ... I didn’t—”

“I ... oh ... I w-w-won’t report you . . . but—”

“I’m sorry,” he whispered. “It — Val, will you marry me? When we get back to Earth, will you marry me?”

“You s-s-s-superstitious oaf!" she gasped. “You blundering idiot!”

Something like pride chilled in him. “Go ahead,” he said dully. “I won’t hide behind your skirts. Go ahead and report me. I suppose it’s regulations you should."

She nodded. Her voice came muffled, where she wept into her hands. “It is. But I . . . can’t.” With a puppet-like jerk of one arm: “Go away! Go away and leave me alone!”

He was halfway down the corridor when he heard her scream.

They gathered in the wardroom, four men clamping fear behind their faces, and looked at her.

“You’re sure?” asked Martin.

Valeria nodded. Her eyes were red, but she spoke in a steady monotone: “Yes. There’s no mistaking that kind of foresight.”

“A meteor swarm,” said Martin. “A meteor swarm on a collision orbit, an hour away.”

Silence was thick between them.

“Can we dodge it?” asked Peralta.

“Oh, yes,” said the girl joylessly. “It’s a big swarm, but fifteen minutes at full acceleration would get us out of its path.”

“And then we’d have to get back on orbit,” said Martin. “We wouldn’t have enough reaction mass left to brake at Mars.”

Dykman turned ponderously in the air. Small light eyes burned at Hall. “It’s your doing.” he said. “You brought this on us.”

“I never —” Hall raised his hands, as if to fend off a blow.

“Oh, yes, you did. You and your superstitions. They nullified our warding spells. What are the chances against this happening by accident, captain?”

“Mighty big,” said Martin. “Mighty big.”

“Out the airlock!” It was a shriek from Peralta.

Hall felt the bulkhead solid at his back. He lifted his fists and said between his teeth: “Because a hysterical female thinks we’re running into danger, you’d kill a man. Well, come on and try it!”

Grayness rode Martin’s voice: “Shut up there. Val, would executing him affect our chances?”

“No,” she said. “It’s too late now.”

Martin regarded her for a long moment, “is that the truth, or are you covering up for the boy?”

“I’m the witch here, skipper!” she flared.

He nodded, as if tired out. “Okay. Okay, I’ll take your word for it. We’re all in this together. It might not be Phil’s fault anyhow. Could just as well be a slip-up at Base, or a foreign warlock, or — Val, is there anything we can do?”

She hung unmoving while a clock hand swept out a full minute. It might have been a century.

“It’s an old comet with a very long-period orbit,” she said then. “That’s why it’s never been encountered before.” Her eyes closed, and her face tautened with strain, and she spoke as if from lightyears away. “There are about a hundred boulder-sized meteors and a lot of cosmic gravel. We can dodge the big ones —”

“But the gravel! It can punch more holes in the ship than we could ever patch.”

“Perhaps," she said, “I can handle the gravel.”

Hall let her open a vein in his wrist and take blood from him as she did from the others. The rest of her preparation was done in secret; he caught a reek of acrid herbs and heard her chanting in some saw- edged language unknown to him.

“Strap in,” said Martin curtly.

He led the girl to the pilot room and buckled her into a recoil chair. Her hair floated red and wild about a head which had become a mask of otherness. Her hands were smeared with blood; she gripped an ivory wand between them and moved it about with strange precision for one whose eyes were shut.

“Take your seat,” she whispered.

Martin strapped in and rested his fingers on the controls. Stray thoughts drifted through his skull: Ginny and the children, a tree they had in their back yard, a farewell party to which all their friends had come. It was a broad and lovely world he had, and bitter to leaye it for an unknown darkness.

Her incantation mumbled forth. Abaddon, Samiel, Ba'al Zebub, Belt Ya’al, all great homed spirits aid us, “The gyros,” she breathed. “Alpha, zero zero three . . . Beta, one zero two . . , Gamma, as is . . . set for thirty-second half-blast—” The ship spun about the axles of the whickering wheels. “Go!”

Thunder and shrieking erupted about them. A troll’s hand thrust them back into the chairs. Then there was again silence and falling.

Martin put his eyes to the periscope hood. He saw one of the meteors, miles away, sunlight wan off its pocked face. Suddenly it had hurtled past, thunderbolt without voice.

“Alpha, five zero one . . . Gamma, zero three three . . . ten-second quarter-blast . . . Go!"

There was a haziness across the hard unwinking stars, a million and a million planetary shards. No bigger than his thumbnail, but at their speed —

“We’re clear of the meteors,” said the toneless witch-throat. “We’ll miss them all on this orbit. But —”

“The little stones. I know, Val. Can you turn them?”

“Get out,” she said.

He unbuckled and pushed from the cabin as softly as possible, closing the door behind him. She was beginning a new chant.

Peralta, Dykman, and Hall turned their eyes to him as he entered the wardroom. Their faces were drained.

“You can crawl out of that webbing if you want, boys,” he told them. “We’re on a free-fall path, safe from the big rocks.”

“But how about the small ones ... the gravel cloud?” Dykman licked sandy lips.

“That’s up to Val.” Martin shrugged. “I saw quite a density; normally, I reckon a thousand or so’d be hitting us. None of ’em are very large, but the relative velocity is up in miles per second.”

They freed themselves and hung in air like fish in a tank. Peralta had his patching kit handy; he could repair a dozen or so leaks. There was no point in donning spacesuits, which only carried two hours’ air supply.

Hall spoke, raggedly; “Captain . . . how do you know there is a swarm out there?”

Martin blinked. “I saw ’em. Looked through the periscope.”

“Did you? Or did you see what you’d hypnotized yourself into seeing?”

There was another stillness. Sweat beaded Hall’s face. He brushed some of it off, and the drops spun cloudily about his head.

“You—” Peralta bunched his legs for a lunge.

“That’ll do!” snapped Martin.

There was a crack like thunder. Their eyes did not register the screak till it was past. Two bullet-holes with melted edges glared at each other across the room, and the air smelled scorched.

Peralta whirled, clapped an adhesive patch over each, and saw internal pressure bulge them. Another explosion resounded down the corridor. He went off to find the punctures.

“Now do you believe?” asked Martin gently.

Hall covered his eyes.

“Two hits,” said Dykman. “Two hits she didn’t stop.”

“There are plenty she did,” answered Martin. He drew a long shuddering breath. “Hang on. We'll be through the cloud, whole or dead, in another couple of minutes.”

Peralta returned. They hung there, waiting. None of them looked at Hall. Now and then the ship clanged like a smitten gong, pebbles bouncing off the hull with too much velocity lost to penetrate.

The supercargo raised his face and stared into hollowness. “It . . . seems ... I was wrong,” he said.

“It’s okay,” said Martin. “You’re just a young fellow, Phil, and your fallacy comes natural. All those historical novels— the Hooverian restoration, Eisenhower’s duel with Hitler, atomic warlocks and naked women in Las Vegas ... I sort of shared your romantic notions myself, once.”

“Fallacy?”

“About science working.”

“But it does! I’ve tried it!”

“Sure it does. The Phobos here is proof enough. But the superstition was this, son: that science could understand everything, and do everything, and make everything good.

“I wonder how they could have had so odd a belief, even then. I wonder how anybody can look at Earth today and believe it. If you say a true concept is one that works, then your science-is-all was false — every radioactive crater, every mutant sickness, every monster born to a woman, proves that!”

They waited.

Valeria came in. Only in null-gravity could she have moved. The high cheekbones stood out as if flesh had been sucked from beneath them.

“We’re safe.” They could barely hear her speak. “I . . . the spells . . . turned the stones away. We’re through them now.”

Her eyes rolled up and she floated motionless. Hall cried aloud, incoherently, and went to her.

Martin, Dykman, and Peralta returned to their posts, to get the ship back on orbit toward Mars.

“It takes a lot out of you,” said Valeria. “But I’ll be all right in a few days.”

Hall gripped her hand. They were alone in the wardroom, only the eyes of the hex signs were there to watch them.

He felt after words. It is never easy to admit you were mistaken. In principle, he still couldn’t.

But . . . He tried to smile. “You needn’t worry about me,” he said. “I’ll believe now that you can do everything.”

“Oh, no. Only a few things,” she replied hastily, and made a two-finger V.

“Enough,” he said. “Enough to see us through. I’m surprised I never realized it before.”

“The Covens don’t operate openly,” she told him. “Magic is best done in private. So all you’ve seen are dances, medicine, public ceremonies. You never saw a homunculus aware of what was happening a hundred miles away. You never saw two warlocks exchange thoughts without speaking, or ... or a witch foreknowing potential trouble spots and deflecting meteors.”

His jaw came forward, stubbornly, “I’m not convinced yet that there isn’t a lot of superstition around,” he said. “I have my doubts about most of the rituals. But I’m willing to be open-minded about them, and look for evidence in each case.”

“That’s sufficient. You’ll make a good spaceman.” Her eyes drooped, and she settled herself into the curve of his arm.

“Telepathy, precognition, psychokinesis, psychosomatics — they were almost ignored in the old days,” he said thoughtfully. “Maybe believed-in rites are necessary to focus the powers, of the mind. Maybe what man has needed was a chance to give them unhindered play, and to study them with the help of the logic which the age of science had developed. ”

Valeria laughed, very softly. “All right,” she said. “If it makes you happier, it you think it’s more scientific, to call magic by such names, go ahead. It’s still magic!”

He tightened his arm about her waist, and she sighed and made no objection. In the face of the oldest magic of all. he didn’t think she would remain a witch very much longer.